The dodo.
Comical, ugly, ridiculous... and extinct.
The most celebrated example of how human beings can wipe out other species.
But the dodo is not alone.
It is part of an ongoing process.
For right now, the Earth is in the middle of a man-made mass extinction.
No species is safe.
But it doesn't have to be that way.
It is within our power to stop this disaster.
And if we don't, it could be we all end up like the dodo.
When you look at the Earth teaming with life, it seems absurd to think that it's teetering on the brink.
But life is fragile, and several times over the last 500 million years, the Earth has been struck by catastrophes that have wiped out most of the life on the planet.
They call them mass extinctions.
If the causes have sometimes been mysterious, in others, the killer left plenty of evidence.
65 million years ago, the Earth was struck by an asteroid.
The fire storm and nuclear winter that followed killed off the dinosaurs and wiped out half the species from what had seemed to be a stable world.
Catastrophic as it was, it wasn't the worst mass extinction to strike the Earth.
For that, you need to go back even further in time.
Looking through the fossil record, palaeontologists have identified five such extinction events.
The most devastating happened at the end of an era called the Permian, 250 million years ago.
This is the dead zone.
This zone represents what it was like here after the mass extinction.
We have never found anything that represents life in this zone.
There is no evidence of plant life, there is no evidence of soils and especially there is no evidence of animals.
This is completely dead.
Never in the history of the planet was there a catastrophe that was so widespread, so devastating, so all-inclusive.
We were going from this very rich place to a biological desert.
From a place like a rainforest, to a place that is composed of a few species, eking out an existence.
95% of the species on the planet were wiped out.
The probable source of this devastation didn't come from outer space, but from within the planet itself.
Today, Siberia is an icy wasteland, but 250 million years ago, the whole area caught fire.
You'd get a huge eruption and another and another, and maybe a lull, and then another bunch of ten, and then another.
All together over a few hundred thousand years.
The Earth is almost continuously spewing out lava until after a million years or so, millions of cubic kilometres have erupted.
So this a truly gigantic volcanic object - thousands, tens of thousands of times larger than anything man has ever seen.
The first effect of the eruption was to make the Earth much colder.
First, we will enter a winter, a volcanic winter.
The dust and the sulphur will cool the atmosphere after each eruption for years, or tens of years.
But the volcanoes also spat out huge amounts of carbon dioxide, which led to a devastating process called global warming.
The carbon dioxide will lead to a greenhouse effect and the cold will be replaced by unusual hot time.
So you get a double hit.
You are cold for a while.
And then hot for a longer time.
..So that, all together, after a million years, the Earth would be different.
The climate would be different and a mass extinction would have happened.
Here is the evidence of how serious global warming can be.
But the ominous thing is that, as we speak, the Earth is going through a sixth mass-extinction event.
One that is happening faster than any of the disasters of the past.
The extinction rate is at crisis proportion, perhaps 100 to 1,000 times higher than before humanity came along.
We see pretty clearly that we could lose a quarter of the species on Earth in the next several decades.
If nothing were done, perhaps half of the species by the end of the century.
That's a crisis.
But this crisis hasn't been caused by a meteorite or a volcano or any natural disaster.
This one is entirely down to one cause... homo sapiens.
Wherever we go, extinction inevitably follows.
It's not surprising, given the way we behave.
It seems the worst thing any species can do is to come into contact with people.
And that, of course, is the big lesson of the dodo.
The dodo is the classic example of man-made extinction.
It all happened 400 years ago on the paradise island of Mauritius in the Indian Ocean.
Today, it seems an unlikely place for a mass murder.
But these excavations are the first to look for dodo bones in 120 years.
And in the mud, they're finding the remains of hundreds of the extinct birds.
What they're revealing is helping to paint a picture of Mauritius before man arrived.
Julian Hume is a palaeontologist at the Natural History Museum.
A world expert on dodos, and the environment they lived in.
This is Mauritius as it may have been before man arrived.
As you can see, it's very very different from what we imagine the place to be today.
Today, sugar cane is everywhere, all of these forest tree species have gone and, unfortunately, most of the animals as well.
Before humans arrived, it would have been dominated by things like giant tortoises, found in their thousands.
Other reptiles as well.
Skinks, this big terrestrial species here, snakes as well.
And in this very special environment we had one very special bird, that is, of course, the dodo.
It would have been a key species in that original environment.
A mile walk through Mauritius would probably have turned up 50 to 100 birds.
But then, in 1598, everything changed.
Humans arrived.
Sailors from Holland.
And the slaughter began.
The minute man arrived on Mauritius, the dodo unfortunately was doomed.
These were desperate men, scurvy was rife, many were sick, they were starving.
When they arrived on the island, there were only two thoughts going through man's mind.
One - can they catch it?
And two - can they eat it?
We know for a fact that men ate dodos.
There are reports of them being taken on board 20 or 50 at a time.
But dodo was not the sought-after gain.
We know that some of the mariners who tried the meat absolutely despised it.
They said it was greasy, and fatty, and totally inedible.
The more they boiled it, the worse it became, the tougher it became.
So it is a myth that the dodo was eaten to extinction.
But tasting foul was not enough to save it.
For humans brought other less direct but more devastating changes to the island.
Unfortunately, animals were introduced, exotic animals that had never been found on Mauritius before.
These included cats, deer, goats, pigs and the worst culprit of all, and inadvertently escaped from ships, was the rat.
These animals spread through the forests, ran wild, and started competing with dodos for their food source, probably attacking eggs and chicks, and also disturbing the nesting cycle of these birds.
All the time, humans were confined to the coast.
They probably weren't seeing dodos at all.
The warfare against the dodo and the other species on Mauritius was taking place the whole time within these unoccupied areas of Mauritius.
Within 80 years of humans and their deadly entourage setting foot on Mauritius, the dodo was gone.
A symbol of man's power to affect the planet.
But the dodo wasn't the beginning of this sixth great mass extinction.
It's been going on as long as modern humans have wandered the Earth.
Once, huge land animals roamed the wild places of the Earth.
10,000 years ago, great herds of woolly mammoths strode across North America.
Then, humans showed up.
In Australia 40,000 years ago there were giant lizards and wombats the size of horses.
But they didn't last long after people arrived.
And in New Zealand, giant flightless birds called moas survived untroubled until just 1,000 years ago.
And then it happened again.
On each continent, within just a few hundreds years of arriving, these small groups of primitive hunters wiped out all the large animals with little more than spears and bows and arrows.
Whilst there is no hard and fast evidence that humans are to blame, there doesn't seem to be any other reasonable explanation.
The one correlation around the world is that the extinctions happened whenever humans arrived.
Let me give an analogy.
Suppose there were 37 unsolved murders in Los Angeles, and you can establish that each of those 37 murders happened just after a certain person, John Smith, entered a building.
That would probably be enough circumstantial evidence to convict John Smith of murder even though we didn't see him shooting the gun at each of those 37 people.
On the same grounds, the fact that these extinctions around the world happened whenever humans arrived in the area, arriving in Australia 40,000 years ago, in the Americas 13,000 years ago, in New Zealand 1,000 years ago, that, I think, is enough to convict humans.
One of the only places you will find large land animals now is in Africa where they evolved alongside humans.
Elephants and rhinos have learned how to live with, and avoid, people.
But even these long-term survivors are now under threat.
Just look at what is happening to the hippos.
Up until recently, they were reasonably abundant.
But they've made it onto the Red List, the list for endangered animals.
The reason for that is...
In the Democratic Republic of Congo they'd the second-largest population in the world, there were 30,000 hippos living in that country.
Within the space of ten years, 95% of that population were wiped out for meat and for ivory.
So, within a decade, that population was decimated.
And it's not just the large animals any more.
Almost everything is suffering from the effects of humans.
And it's getting worse.
We are now seeing rates of extinction of maybe 50 to 150 species per day are disappearing off the face of the Earth.
That is far in excess of anything we have seen historically.
In the recent Red List, they were showing that 25% of all mammals on the planet are endangered, one in three amphibians will go, one in eight birds.
So these are things we are accustomed to seeing and they're highly endangered.
The current rate of extinction is even faster than the Permian.
Of course, there is a school of thought that says we really don't have anything to worry about.
They say that nature is all about competition and extinction is just a natural part of that process.
Natural-history museums the world over are monuments to animals that have lost their battle with nature.
Some of them were the greatest ever to walk the Earth.
We have a fossil record which goes back for no less than 3,000 million years.
It tells us beyond any question that species always eventually go extinct.
It is a normal, inevitable part of the process of evolution.
We don't know what percentage of the species which ever lived are still alive today but 1%, maybe 1 in 1,000, as few as that.
All the rest have gone extinct.
Over 99% of all of the creatures that have ever lived are now extinct.
And most of them never came into contact with humans.
Even the top dogs, the species which look like they'd go on for ever, were all eventually snuffed out.
Let me give you an example.
Up to about 200 million years ago, there was a group of animals called the mammal-like reptiles.
They were far and away the dominant terrestrial animals walking the surface of the Earth.
This is an example of one of these creatures which was clearly carnivorous.
You can see the wonderfully sharp teeth and the big canines.
Its main prey would have been things like this animal here - the herbivores of the time.
They would be living in big herds, they would be grazing, a little like the sort of mammals one would see in the savannah in Africa today.
The scene would look rather like that.
One would have supposed they would last for ever.
By about 200 million years ago, a new group had appeared, which we call the dinosaurs.
They seem to have been better adapted at life on land.
And, relatively quickly, the mammal-like reptiles had disappeared, gone extinct, and the dinosaurs had taken over.
The lesson from this would seem to be that extinction just happens.
And there is nothing anyone can do about it.
There are a few exceptions - creatures which have survived for hundreds of millions of years.
But there seem to be no common features that explain why they're still here.
Horseshoe crabs have been virtually unchanged for 300 million years.
They've survived the Permian disaster, the asteroid that killed the dinosaurs, climate change, ice ages and, so far, humanity.
Scientists have spent years trying to find out if they can teach us about survival.
But with no success.
We can perhaps say that it was its adaptability, its resistance to predation, which allowed it to survive.
Quite why it managed to survive the environmental changes over this long period of time is, I have to say, really quite a mystery.
So perhaps, in the natural course of events, extinction and survival is just a matter of chance.
There are patterns in this current extinction that suggest there is more than just luck at work.
That some animals are particularly vulnerable to human activity.
And one factor is clearer than any other.
A role call of extinctions over the last 400 years tells a sorry story - Madeiran wood pigeon, Canary Islands giant rat, Puerto Rican shrew, the Hawaiian honey creeper, Samoan wood rail, the Javan tiger, Seychelles parakeet, the Cyprus dipper.
All of these creatures lived on islands quite happily number the arrival of humans.
In fact, the isolation probably helped them survive.
But island life is also the evolutionary equivalent of moving to a gated retirement community.
Once you have been there for a while, you lose the ability to cope with the outside world.
Once again, the dodo is the perfect example.
The dodo's forebears looked like this Nicabar pigeon when they first arrived in Mauritius.
A million years of evolution later and that pigeon was completely unrecognisable.
The wings had all but gone, the beak had grown, and the chest had puffed out.
Today, it looks comic.
But the dodo was perfectly adapted to its island home.
Why would something like the dodo lose the ability to fly?
Well, actually, to produce flight is very expensive in terms of energy for birds.
Now, imagine an ancestral pigeon landing on somewhere like Mauritius, an isolated volcanic island, no predators, all the food it requires is on the ground, it doesn't need to fly.
The bird could get fatter, store more weight and, over time, evolve into this giant ground pigeon.
The dodo was beautifully adapted to its island home.
But once humans arrived, it couldn't adapt quickly enough to the changes they brought.
The dodo had become specialised.
Predators from elsewhere arrive on the island, the dodo cannot cope.
It cannot change millions of years of evolution in a very short time.
It's a story that has been retold on islands around the world.
More than half of the species that have become extinct in modern times lived on islands.
..Until they were visited by humans.
Many of them, like the dodo, were flightless birds.
Most oceanic islands had one or two species.
Now, they are almost all gone.
Some, like this Laysan rail from Hawaii, survived into the 20th century.
Before they scuttled off into extinction.
But even birds that can fly perfectly well are not safe.
The island of Guam once had a thriving bird population until, in the 1940s, brown tree snakes were imported on boats.
The birds had no idea what to do when confronted with the snakes.
Rather than fly away, they just sat there.
Today, over 80% of Guam's forest bird species are extinct.
But the most famous human-caused bird extinction didn't happen on an island, it happened in America.
It was the passenger pigeon.
The easiest target in the world.
The decline of the passenger pigeon is the most dramatic decline of any creature we know of.
At the start of the 19th century, it was probably the commonest bird on Earth.
The birds lived in enormous flocks of many millions.
They blackened the sky, made so much noise, you couldn't even hear a man shouting, so many wings were beating in the sky.
These enormous flocks would cause immense destruction to crops and trees, anything that got in the way.
They were a plague of locusts.
So when passenger pigeons arrived in a particular area, people were fairly horrified.
They were incredibly easy to shoot.
You'd get a gun and just aim it the sky, and you just pull the trigger and you bring down passenger pigeons every time you shot.
Most birds would instinctively fly away from the hunters' guns, but not the passenger pigeon.
In fact, it was impossibly easy to attract the birds.
You would catch a passenger pigeon, tie it to a pole and its squawks would attract the other birds.
The decoys had a name - they were called stool pigeons.
They lured millions of their species to their deaths.
We are quite savage beasts.
The thought of killing, say, 5,000 birds in a couple of afternoons does not disturb many people.
It may disturb you, me, it may disturb thousands of others but it doesn't disturb everybody.
Such was the combination of the pigeons' suicidal nature and the hunters' savagery, that within just 50 years, at the end of the 19th century, their numbers declined from six billion to just one individual.
A fall in population of 250,000 birds every day.
When the numbers drop below a certain level, even though that level may have been many, many millions, it was doomed, even though it was still incredibly common.
The numbers just spiralled down and down and down until the only remaining birds were a few that had been captured.
The last one was called Martha, named after George Washington's wife.
She died in September 1914 in the Cincinnati Zoo.
The final straw for the poor old passenger pigeon was that once it was in trouble, it couldn't breed fast enough to keep its numbers up.
The speed with which animals reproduce can have a huge effect on what species survive and which fall to extinction.
Some species can wipe out others just by having sex.
In 1859, humans introduced just 24 rabbits to Australia.
No-one meant it to happen.
But 100 years later, there were 600 million of them.
It was colonisation by sheer force of numbers.
Many native species were lost but it was a triumph for the rabbit.
In contrast, the inability to breed effectively is currently sounding the death knell for many creatures.
..Most notably the panda.
Human pressure has already exposed its vulnerability.
Fragmenting its habitat and decimating its numbers.
But the heart of their problem is that they seem strangely unsuited to survival.
It starts with their diet.
The giant panda is an absolute curious beast.
It's a bear.
By all rights it's a carnivore but it spends all of its time eating bamboo.
That's not a particularly highly calorific food stuff.
In fact, it's estimated that pandas only get 10% of the goodness out of the bamboo it eats because its digestive system is not designed to digest bamboo.
What that means is that they have to spend a huge amount of time eating.
A fully-grown panda can eat anything from 15 to 50 kilos of bamboo a day, which is up to half of its bodyweight in a day.
This is not a productive use of its time.
And because it's so low in energy, they tend to be lethargic, so they spend most of the time just sitting down and eating.
And it's not just their diet.
Pandas are simply terrible at sex.
They just don't have the urge.
They're not the best lovers and reproducers in the world.
They can't learn unless they see other pandas having sex, because they're solitary.
The issue comes actually for the panda to understand how to have sex.
What positions you adopt in order to be successful and so on.
Unless they have exposure to learn that somehow, I think it will always be problematic.
And to make it even worse, they're very rarely fertile.
The females only come into heat once a year, normally in about April, in the spring, there's a window of 3-4 days when she can actually conceive.
In the period leading up to that, both sexes tend to become more vocal.
They scent mark a lot more to excite one another.
But even doing those things, in many cases, either they don't have sex at all or, if they do, it may not be successful.
It may seem hard to blame humans for the decline of a creature that seems so ill-adapted to survival.
In fact, humans have been trying their best to help pandas breed.
We've made them watch panda pornography!
And have slipped Viagra into their food.
More recently, IVF methods have been adapted so that pandas don't have to make any effort at all.
And it's been a resounding success.
In the Chinese sanctuaries, baby pandas are being popped out like champagne corks.
Typically, no-one is more surprised at the success than the pandas themselves!
And this is the most bizarre element of the present mass extinction.
Human beings are not just being destructive.
This is the only mass extinction where the cause of death is also trying to undo what it has done.
So is it possible that we could reverse the whole extinction process?
One of the main ways to stave off extinction is captive breeding programmes.
Around the world, zoos like London Zoo dedicate a lot of their time and money to saving some of world's most endangered species.
And it's not just the glamorous species that are being saved.
There are probably more endangered species in this room in terms of number of individuals within those species than there is in any comparable space on the planet.
They're all Polynesian tree snails, from French Polynesia.
They're part of a group of snails called partula snails.
The partula tree snails were forced towards extinction by a series of human-related catastrophes.
50 years ago, the partula were the only snails in Polynesia.
But then humans introduced giant African land snails.
The theory was that they would be good to eat.
Unfortunately, they weren't.
And before anyone knew it, they were everywhere.
In an attempt to control the plague of snails, yet more snails were introduced.
This time, the cannibalistic rosy wolf snail.
And that was the second disaster.
They have these receptors, these long moustache on each side of the snail's head which they can wave about.
We called them fu manchu snails because they have a long... moustache.
The trouble was that fu manchu didn't want to eat the giant African snails.
They did develop a taste for the natives partulas.
They can travel several times faster than your normal snail can, so they can find these snails very efficiently.
They are very good hunters.
They can eat their way through an estimated eight partulas a day.
You can imagine the impact they actually had.
Before long, we were seeing whole species becoming wiped out.
Luckily, some people were alert to the partula's plight.
As the carnivorous snails swept across the island, a rescue operation swung into action.
In some cases, we would get to ends of valleys, these high volcanic valleys and then find that the actual predator was just sweeping through the last areas of the parts where you found the snails and we would collect the last handful.
It was the last possible moment where they could be rescued.
Saved from their island paradise, the snails have been nurtured and bred in these bare glass tanks for the last 15 years and now they are thriving.
Rather than just a handful of snails, now there are enough of some of the species to fill a bucket.
Enough to guarantee their survival.
But not every snail could be brought back from the brink, like poor partula turgida.
Unfortunately, on 1st January 1996, turgida was found dead in the morning.
I was the one who saw it unfortunately.
Despite our best efforts, they just fizzled out.
They didn't respond to the breeding effort.
So, it's obviously very, very sad.
You've done what you could, you gave it a chance.
The snails had been lucky enough to get their chance but captive breeding can only be part of the answer.
There's just not room in the world's zoos to house all of the endangered species...
..Especially the bigger ones.
We may have to put the future of some species on ice.
This is a frozen arc.
This one is in London Zoo.
A few skin cells frozen in here may protect a species from extinction for ever.
As long as some precious DNA is preserved, it may one day be possible to bring the animals back to life by the power of cloning.
In fact, it's already happening.
This is no ordinary calf.
It's a rare banteng from Java and it's a clone.
A clone made from the cells of animal that died in San Diego Zoo in 1980.
This is Jurassic Park stuff.
If we can clone animals that have been dead for more than 20 years, how much further back could we go?
Could we even clone animals that are already extinct?
Could the DNA preserved in dodo bones be used to bring them back to life 400 years after the last one died?
Sadly, there are limits.
They're not going to clone a dodo.
It's not possible to clone a dodo.
It seems that despite the science fiction, the quality of DNA from dodo bones just isn't good enough.
Ancient DNA is preserved best in bones that are preserved in very cold and very dry conditions.
The warmer the environment, the more difficult it is to recover DNA.
We can only get very, very small fragments.
For the dodo, we were only to get one hundred or so bases at a time.
Our genomes have more than three billion bases in them.
In order to clone the animal, you would have to be able to extract everything in those one hundred base fragments, figure out how to piece them together, figure out how to wrap them up, figure out where they go, figure out how to get them into the nucleus and then find an actual host that would be usable to develop this extinct animal.
There is an argument that there would be no point reviving creatures that have already died out.
Why would we want to do it?
Where are they going live?
What is the point in bringing back an animal whose habitat is destroyed, who don't have any others of the same species to associate with, so we can bring back and stick them in a zoo, walk on by and wave at it.
What is the point of all of this?
Shouldn't we be spending this money actually protecting the species that are still alive?
So, for the foreseeable future at least, human efforts will largely be confined to the species that are still alive.
The trouble is that this scientific effort is often undone by those with far baser motives.
Because, there are those who think animals are worth more dead than alive.
The illegal trade in wildlife is the third largest illegal trade in the world.
Drugs being first, illegal arms and armaments second, and then the illegal wildlife trade.
It is estimated between 5-110 billion dollars a year.
It's a massive trade.
It's a trade that is growing every year.
This shawl comes from the Tibetan antelope, or the chiru.
They kill the antelope and pluck the fine wool off the skin.
This will sell between £1,500 to £2,000 retail in the United Kingdom.
It's been hunted at a level of 20,000 animals a year.
It's estimated there are only 80,000 animals left now.
This is a rhino horn... made into a dagger.
The handle here is made of rhino horn.
This is why the rhino was poached to near extinction.
Ivory.
You can tell that it's ivory purely from the smoothness that you have.
You can tell from some of the yellowing that goes on that it's a genuine ivory item.
If I show you on a tusk.
You can see where it matches the curvature of the ivory tusk.
A monitor lizard, it's been made into a handbag.
You can see how tasteless this item is completely.
If you open it up, you can actually see the back legs as well.
Hundreds of species are affected by the trade in wildlife parts.
There is one animal that is suffering more than most.
Such is the demand for tiger parts that it has been pushed to the brink of extinction.
On the Thames, just next to MI6, another group of spooks is monitoring the trade in tiger parts, and what they're finding is that it's getting worse.
Because of the internet.
The internet is easy, it's cheap and anonymous.
It makes it very attractive for people to buy and sell products, especially if they might be illegal products.
One of the biggest problems is the high-tech end of a very old-fashioned business.
Traditional Chinese medicine.
A key ingredient of which is tiger bone.
Here we've got hu gu tonic.
Hu gu is the pinion for tiger bone.
It's willing to sell you four packs for $126 and you can click to "add to cart", and then you are committing an offence, you are buying an endangered species.
The demand for tiger bone products is almost insatiable.
A single seizure of bones in Taiwan contained the remains of 5% of the world's Sumatran tigers.
If the trade in tigers continues as it does now, tigers could be extinct within the next 15 to 20 years, by the next generation.
It's very, very sobering thought.
We have to act now if we are to stop them disappearing from the wild for ever.
So this is where humanity has got to.
We are at a crossroads.
If we carry on as we are now, cutting down the forests, polluting the rivers, introducing alien species around the world, and pumping filth into the atmosphere, then the mass extinction will continue.
But, uniquely, we have it in our power to reverse the process.
The issue is do we have the will?
Because if we don't, it is possible that we too will join the ranks of the extinct.
It doesn't matter how intelligent we are, if things get beyond a certain point, nothing will save us.
I think human beings are a failed species.
We are on the way out.
We are flawed.
Our intelligence isn't of the kind that is compatible with nature.
We are living too wrong.
We are breaking all the rules.
Our lives are so artificial that they can't possibly be sustained within the limits of our particular planet.
Like any species that's got something wrong with it, nature is going to get the better of it and see to it that it becomes extinct.
It's an extreme view.
But Professor Boulter believes we are stretching the planet's ability to support us and that we will wipe ourselves out, just as we once did to the dodo.
Because it is possible that we are not going be able to cope with the changes we are forcing on the Earth.
There are twice as many of us as there were 50 years ago.
We are all consuming more, warming the planet.
Unless we stop, the equatorial regions will turn into deserts.
And as sea levels rise, there will be less and less land to support us.
What will we eat?
Where will we grow it?
With famine comes war.
And they are followed by plague and pestilence.
As more and more people cram into a smaller space, disease will spread.
We will need medicine but where will we get it from?
Many medicines are derived from tropical plants.
As they are swallowed by the desert, where will we turn?
It could all be leading to disaster.
It might seem far-fetched, but it has happened before.
History is littered with civilisations that collapsed because of the damage they did to the environment.
The Maya thrived in the jungles of Central America, until they reached the point where the land could support them no longer.
Easter island was once covered in forest.
But people cut down the trees to help build their statues.
Only when they were all gone did they realise they couldn't live without them.
These statues stand as a testimony to what happens to those who destroy their environment.
I think it would be a grave injustice to speak of the human species as in some sense evil.
Even though we are destroying the environment so efficiently at the present time.
Basically, that's not our intent, it never was.
It was necessary for survival for the ancestral human being to throw everything they had against the wilderness in an attempt to conquer it, to utilise it, to open it, for new populations.
And for millions of years, that paid off without undo damage to the environment.
But then what happened was we succeeded too well.
And at long last we broke nature.
If we are unable to undo the damage we have caused, some think that the best thing that could happen to the planet is for humans to die out.
The planet would, of course, be delighted for humans to become extinct!
The sooner it happens the better.
There's no question that the planet would go wild with celebration.
The other species would be pleased to be rid of us.
It might seem like a glum future for humans but perhaps not for the planet as a whole.
Without us, life would still go on.
It's in times of dramatic catastrophe that extinctions take place.
It's there that there are opportunities for evolution to start new groups, within the new environmental opportunities that catastrophe has given.
One of the great things about life is its resilience and with humans out of the way, life could bounce back remarkably quickly.
After a few years, the seas will start to fill with fish again.
The forests will start to regrow and as our cities crumble, the air will be filled with bird song once more.
Within just a few centuries, the planet will forget about us.
A natural order will be restored.
There was some work I was involved in some years ago, where we found a new continent.
35 million years ago, this new continent suddenly emerged out of the sea.
And it lasted until about 10 million years ago and then suddenly the North Atlantic got wider and this continent submerged again.
There are no mountains, there is no connection to any other land, but there are plants, seeds and things that have blown there, there were birds and there are other invertebrates living there.
It must have been a very pleasant, peaceful place.
It's that concept that I often think the Earth is trying to attain.
That is the kind of environment it wants for itself.
And I think that's kind of place that it will turn back to once the present catastrophe has passed.
That's the way the Earth will be again - just as nature intended.
It might be a lovely place, just we won't be there to see it.
Unless we change our ways.